A Guide to the Records of the Columbia Heights Civic Association, 2003-2007
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Records of the Columbia Heights Civic Association, 2003-2007
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 311
2 boxes.
Columbia Heights Civic Association
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Sara Collins in 2007.
Historical Information
The Columbia Heights Civic Association (CHCA), founded in 1976, was very active in the 1980s and early 1990s. It was resuscitated in 2001 by neighbors who were "committed to pursuing a Neighborhood Conservation Plan to institute positive changes in our area." Columbia Heights is located in South Arlington, bounded on the north by Columbia Pike, on the west by Walter Reed Drive, on the east by S. Rolfe Street and on the south by 16th Street South and property owned by the Army Navy Country Club. In 2004, the CHCA published the Columbia Heights Neighborhood Conservation Plan in cooperation with the Department of Community Planning, Housing and Development Department of Arlington County.
Scope and Content
Record Group 311 consists of CHCA correspondence and internal documents such as minutes and bylaws, plus related correspondence and documents by local government, businesses, civic organizations, and individuals. The materials are dated 2003-2007 and measure .6 linear feet. Important topics are Safeway supermarket encroachment agreements and the Arlington Village Condominiums budget and covenants (both with copies of legal forms). Also of note are the Form Based Code from the Columbia Pike Revitalization Organization (CPRO) and the development of Penrose Square (both with plans and published material).
Arrangement
The material is arranged in 27 folders by subject matter, all in one series. The files were organized and labeled by the CHCA, except for material that was loose at the bottom of the box. This consisted of two groups of material, one dealing with Arlington Town Center and the other with Penrose Square. Folder titles are from the CHCA, except those in brackets [ ], which have been titled by the archivist.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
More information on the Columbia Pike area is in RG 126, Columbia Pike Revitalization Organization Records. Many other Arlington civic associations have collections throughout the Arlington Community Archives.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Citizens' associations; Community organization.; Columbia Heights (Arlington, Va.); Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Organizational Materials
  - CHCA Bylaws [Columbia Heights Civic Association], 2006-2007 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Agenda CHCA, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Attendance, 2005 (Box 1)
  - NCAC [Neighborhood Conservation Advisory Committee], 2005 (Box 1)
  - Water Main, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Planning Commission, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Public Spaces Master Plan, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Arlington Village, 1991, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  - County Letter, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Safeway, 2005 (Box 1)
  - [Safeway -2- Encroachment Applications], 2005 (Box 1)
  - Glebe, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  - North Tract Park, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Parking, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  - Civic Fed, 2004-2006 (Box 1)
  - Covenants (1), 2006 (Box 1)
  - Covenants (2), 2006 (Box 2)
  - Covenants (3), 2006 (Box 2)
  - Dog Park, 2005-2006 (Box 2)
  - CPRO, Columbia Pike Revitalization Organization (1), 2003 (1) (Box 2)
  - CPRO, Columbia Pike Revitalization Organization (2), 2003 (2) (Box 2)
  - Form Based Code, 2005-2006 (Box 2)
  - Bridge, 2005-2006 (Box 2)
  - Walter Reed Center, n.d. (Box 2)
  - [Arlington Town Center], 2006 (Box 2)
  - [Penrose Square], 2006 (Box 2)